Monsignor Stanislaus Musiel Collection CPAA 95.11
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Monsignor Stanislaus Musiel Collection
1904-1988
CPAA 95.11
Connecticut Polish American Archives
2.0 Linear feet
Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel was born in Poland, attended seminary in Louvain, Belgium and was appointed for pastoral work in Hartford diocese, Connecticut. He was a pastor at St. Cyril and Methodius parish in Hartford from 1917 till his death in 1966. Material in the collection illustrates Msgr. Musiel appointments in various parishes in Connecticut and decades of pastoral work in SS. Cyril and Methodius parish in Hartford. Collection consists of correspondence, publications and photographs related to Msgr. Musiel. Substantial part of the collection's material relates to Msgr. Musiel's relatives from Kazowski and Boniarczyk families.
Musiel, Stanislaus
Scope and Contents note
Collection includes Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel correspondence, clippings about him and his SS. Cyril and Methodius parish, anniversary publications, large collection of family and parish photographs. Large part of the collection consists of personal papers of his sister-in-law Mrs. Zofia Musiel Boniarczyk and her husband Karol Boniarczyk. Also included are records and personal papers of Zofia’s siblings, Wanda Kazowska and her brother Jozef Kazowski. Collection covers the years 1904 to 1988.
Biographical/Historical note
Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel was born in Poland in 1872 and received his education there up to the secondary level. He was enrolled in the seminary in Louvain, Belgium and he graduated in 1897. In Louvain he was assigned to the Hartford diocese, Connecticut, to help in pastoral work with Polish immigrants. His first parish was at St. Francis in Torrington, then St. Peter's in Hartford. Msgr. Musiel organized parishes in New London, New Haven, and Middletown. He was appointed to be a pastor at St. Cyril and Methodius in Hartford in 1917, where he stayed until his death in 1966. In 1939 he was raised to the rank of Domestic Prelate. In 1942, while celebrating his 25th anniversary as pastor of SS. Cyril and Methodius, he was presented with the Golden Cross, the highest award of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. Msgr. Musiel was very active in many Polish American organizations. He established several associations and committees to help new immigrants and to keep Polonia together. In recognition for his work for Polish American cause he was awarded the medal "Polonia Restituta" in 1959 by the Polish government in exile in London. He also served as a director for St. Francis Hospital in Hartford. Rev. Musiel died after short illness on January 15, 1966 at the age of 93. He was buried at Secret Heart Cemetery in New Britain, Connecticut.
Joseph Kazowski (1898-1995?)was Musiel’s second cousin, who came to the United States under the Displaced Person’s Act from Poland in 1948, and was sponsored by Msgr. Musiel. Jozef Kazowski had law degree from Poland and practiced law until WWII started. He served in the Polish Army and was a POW in Germany. After coming to the US he worked as a parish secretary, and was active in Polish American life taking courses at local colleges and making monetary and literary donations to Polish American causes. Wanda Stanislawa Kazowska (1899-1974), Joseph’s sister, was born in Poland and came to the United States in 1939. She worked for Pratt & Whitney Aircraft Division in East Hartford as a laboratory technician. Zofia Kazowski Musiel Boniarczyk (1897-1988), oldest of the Kazowski siblings, was married to Dr. Joseph Musiel, brother of Msgr. Musiel, until 1937 when he died in Gniezno, Poland. She came to the US in 1939 and in 1957 married Korol Boniarczyk. She served as the executor to Msgr. Musiel’s will. Karol Boniarczyk (1902-1962), born in Austria, married Zofia in 1957. He served as a captain of the medical section. After the war he worked as a physician and lived in New York.
Arrangement note
Material in the collection is arranged in two series. First series consists of material related to Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel, and second series consists of material related to the Boniarczyk and Kazowski family. Both families were related to Msgr. Musiel. Jozef Kazowski was in the possession of all materials and from his estate the material was donated to the archives by Mrs. Elizabeth Wasiutynski in 1995.
Boniarczyk, Zofia Musiel; Catholics -- Polish; Clergy -- Connecticut; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Displaced Persons Act of 1948; Immigrants -- Connecticut; Photographs; Poland -- Emigration and immigration; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- History; Scrapbook; SS. Cyril and Methodius Parish (Hartford, Conn.)-History; World War, 1939-1945 -- Poland
- Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel papers.
  - Short biography of Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel and related clippings, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Msgr. Musiel - Passports and catholic ID, 1897-1899, 1927, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Msgr. Musiel - naturalization certificate, November 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Msgr. Musiel - appointment to SS. Cyril and Methodius parish, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rev. Musiel's nomination to Domestic Prelate, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel - Golden Jubilee booklet 1897-1947, June 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel - Golden Jubilee 2 commemorative plaques from the Bishop of Hartford and Mayor of Hartford, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel - photographs from Golden Jubilee of priesthood, June 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Msgr. Musiel - Polonia Restituta medal, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Msgr. Musiel guest book - signatures of prominent people visiting Msgr. Musiel, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Msgr. Musiel guest book from 90th Birthday celebration, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Msgr. Musiel correspondence, 1949-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Msgr. Musiel income (stocks and bonds), 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Msgr. Musiel - obituaries and related correspondence and clippings. Short letter from Harry S. Truman, the governor, senator, and mayor of Hartford enclosed., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Msgr. Musiel funeral photos, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Msgr. Musiel Last Will (2 copies), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Msgr. Musiel - inventory of the estate, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Polish National Fund medals for Msgr. Musiel and Zofia Musiel Boniarczyk and "St. Casimir 500 years” pewter pin., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Msgr. Musiel - formal photographs, 1960's (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Msgr. Musiel - photographs of dignitaries and special guests, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Msgr. Musiel - photographs from family and community events, and church celebrations (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Msgr. Musiel and Zofia M. Boniarczyk - Quit Claim Deed, 1961, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 11 Postcards - Presentation of flags to 1st Division of Polish Army in France, June 22, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rev. Stefan Plywaczyk (New Jersey priest) - obituaries (d. 1981), 1972, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Prayer cards for various funerals, 1922-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Oddzial Stowarzyszenia Lotnikow Polskich w U.S.A. fotografia z Parady Pulaskiego” (Polish Pilots Association during the Pulaski Parade) written on back of photograph, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Polish Catholic items, 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Boniarczyk and Kazowski family papers., This series contains material related to Boniarczyk and Kazowski family, relatives of Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel.
  - Msgr. S. Musiel - affidavit of support and other documents re: J.Kazowski immigration under Displaced Persons Act of 1948. Income tax records for Musiel in 1948, Reference letter from The Hartford Connecticut Trust Company. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jozef Kazowski - personal documents, immigration papers., Bulk, 1947-1953; 1939-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jozef Kazowski - 3 letters received in Oflag, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jozef Kazowski - photo in "The Munich American", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Wanda Stanislawa Kazowska - certificate of Naturalization (1948), passport (1971), photos, small notebook with written notes, certificate of donation made in her memory to a scholarship fund., 1940-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wanda Kazowska - last will, certification of death, 1968, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Wanda Kazowska - inventory of her estate (1974), tax documents, affidavit for Jozef Kazowski, 1948, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Wanda Kazowska and Zofia Musiel trip on Batory, an ocean liner, from Gdansk to New York City and related correspondence, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Zofia Musiel-Boniarczyk and Charles Boniarczyk trip to Poland., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Polski Komitet Imigracyjny (Polish American Immigration and Relief Committee) fundraiser - Zofia Boniarczyk involvement., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Karol Boniarczyk – (Charles) Canadian passport (1957) and ID in the Polish Army 1939, 1939, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Karol Boniarczyk - obituaries, in memoriam, certificate of death, social security card, admission to United States card. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Karol Boniarczyk - Krzyz Walecznych (Cross of Valor), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Zofia Musiel - Edmund Liszka, work contract for Liszka's radio station, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Zofia M. Musiel and Charles Boniarczyk - marriage certificate, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Zofia M. Boniarczyk - death certificate March 1,1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Karol Boniarczyk – paystubs from the Home and Hospitals of the Daughters of Israel, Inc., 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Zofia Musiel-Boniarczyk, correspondence re: Rev. Musiel estate., 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Zofia Musiel-Boniarczyk last will., 1949, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Zofia Musiel-Boniarczyk - correspondence, 1951-1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Zofia Musiel-Boniarczyk-passports., 1939, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Karol Boniarczyk - correspondence., 1950-1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Karol Boniarczyk - photos, 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Karol Boniarczyk - Minister Zawisza's visit in US., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - “Easter time in Poland”, an essay, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1951, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Prayer booklets, 1931, 1950, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook - clippings related to Poland and the World War II, 1939-1941 (Box 4)
  - Msgr. Stanislaus Musiel - portraits (mounted), 1960's (Box 4)
  - Karol Boniarczyk - official document, from the Polish President-in-exile, decorating Karol Boniarczyk with the Cross of Valor., 1962 (Box 4)